{"tossups": [{"question": "This man is inaccurately depicted leading a mob that tars and feathers a British official in the <em>John Adams</em> miniseries. He preceded Samuel Adams as the penultimate colonial governor of Massachusetts. This man's main cargo vessel was seized by the <em>HMS Romney</em>, leading him to become particularly active in the Sons of Liberty. For the point, name this man whose endorsement of the Declaration of Independence made his name a term for any signature.", "answer": "John <b><u>Hancock</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Andreas Baader and Ulrike Meinhof (<b>ul-REE-keh MINE-hofe</b>) co-founded a terrorist organization with this adjective in its name that killed American soldiers stationed in West Germany. Another group with this adjective in its name kidnapped and murdered Italian prime minister Aldo Moro. An army of this color invaded Poland from the east as part of the Molotov-Ribbentrop pact and later fought the Germans on the Eastern Front. For the point, name this predominant color of the Soviet flag.", "answer": "<b><u>red</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "These people are the antagonists of Martin Sherman's play <em>Bent</em>, and spy Howard Campbell is put on trial for being one of these people in Kurt Vonnegut's <em>Mother Night</em>. The consequences of these people's rise and fall provide the second half of the novel <em>The Tin Drum</em>, and a factory owner attempting to sabotage these people is the protagonist of <em>Schindler's List</em>. For the point, name these people who ultimately find and imprison the author of <em>The Diary of Anne Frank</em>", "answer": "<b><u>Nazis</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Germans</u></b>, etc.]", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Famous plaintiffs in this kind of courtroom included Stella Liebeck, who won a 1994 verdict after suffering burns from coffee at McDonalds. This kind of law works differently in Louisiana than in the rest of the U.S., as the Code Napoleon is the basis for a statutory system there, which differs from the British-derived common law used elsewhere. For the point, name this kind of law that involves suits brought by individuals for torts, as opposed to criminal law.", "answer": "<b><u>civil</u></b> law [or <b><u>common</u></b> law before it is read; or <b><u>tort</u></b> law before it is read]", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "Troops fighting in this war cried, \"Remember the Raisin!\" In the run-up to this war, new Congressmen such as Felix Grundy were accused of \"land-hunger.\" This war was caused by events such as the <em>Chesapeake-Leopard</em> affair and similar examples of impressment, as well as by Henry Clay's War Hawks. For the point, name this war in which the Canadian city of York and Washington, D.C. were both burned, which ended inconclusively in 1814.", "answer": "War of <b><u>1812</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In Hellenic tradition, Thales of Miletus was among this number of \"Sages.\" In the century AD of this number, Empress Wu's reign interrupted the relatively new Tang dynaty. This many Cities of Gold were sought in North America by Spanish explorer Francisco de Coronado. A grouping of this many landmarks includes the temple of Artemis at Ephesus and the Mausoleum of Halicarnassus. For the point, give the canonical number of Wonders of the Ancient World.", "answer": "<b><u>seven</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Because this site had no holes cut out to fire guns through, a catwalk system was hastily constructed under the direction of Green Jameson. James Neill complained of a lack of funding for the defense of this site, where the slave Joe and Susanna Dickinson were spared. Similar events as what happened at this site occurred at the Battle of Goliad. For the point, Jim Bowie and Davy Crockett died at what San Antonio mission during the Texas revolution?", "answer": "the <b><u>Alamo</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An exception to this Constitutional amendment which was applied in the 1940s and 1950s was established in the <em>Chaplinsky v. New Hampshire</em> case. This amendment was also the subject of the <em>West Virginia v. Barnette</em> decision and the draft card case <em>U.S. v. O'Brien</em>. This amendment is held to imply a right to freedom of association, and it begins with the Establishment Clause. For the point, name this Constitutional amendment, which protects freedom of religion and speech.", "answer": "<b><u>First</u></b> Amendment", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this state, a gangster raid on the FBI to free Frank Nash resulted in the Union Station Massacre. This state was home to Tom Pendergast's political machine, which helped Harry Truman early in his career. Mormons were subject to an \"extermination order\" in this state, which caused a \"bell in the night\" when it was admitted to the Union alongside Maine. For the point, identify this Midwestern state and namesake of an 1820 \"compromise.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Missouri</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A politician from this city reorganized its four traditional tribes into ten new <em>phyles</em> and increased the size of its ruling council by 100. Later reforms in this city moved judicial power to the <em>boule</em> (<b>BOO-lay</b>) from its original court, the Areopagus. For the point, name this city where harsh laws instituted by Draco were eventually reformed by Cleisthenes (<b>KLISE-then-eez</b>) and Solon, who laid the foundations for its democracy.", "answer": "<b><u>Athens</u></b> [or <b><u>Athenai</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In a film set during this war, a man is rejected from joining an army because he a Western and Atlantic Railroad engineer. In that film set during this war, the <em>Texas</em> is driven onto the burning Rock River Bridge. This war was the subject of the Buster Keaton film <em>The General</em>, and this war\u2019s attack on Fort Wagner was the subject of the film <em>Glory</em>. For the point, name this war depicted in Mathew Brady's <em>The Dead at Antietam</em>.", "answer": "American <b><u>Civil War</u></b> [or the War <b><u>Between the States</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "George Cayley built a working model of this device, but could not create one large enough to fit a human. In 1877, Enrico Forlanini built the first working example of this kind of machine, which was eventually perfected by Heinrich Focke and Igor Sikorsky. An iconic image of these vehicles shows them removing refugees during the fall of Saigon. For the point, name these flying vehicles which use rotors and propellers as opposed to fixed wings.", "answer": "heli<b><u>copter</u></b>s [or <b><u>chopper</u></b>s or other synonyms]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This award was named in 1935 in honor of a man who led the Downtown Athletic Club, where this award was formerly presented. Charlie Ward, who went on to play in the NBA, won this award in 1993 for excellence in a different sport. Steve Spurrier became the first recipient of this award to later coach a winner of it when Danny Wuerfel of Florida won it in 1996. For the point, name this trophy, the highest individual award in American college football, won by Tim Tebow in 2007.", "answer": "<b><u>Heisman</u></b> Trophy", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Proponents of this activity included a soil chemistry pioneer who discovered the value of spreading marl to neutralize acidic soil, Edmund Ruffin. An attempt to create new areas for practicing this activity was advocated in the Ostend Manifesto while the Wilmot Proviso sought to limit it in areas acquired from Mexico. For the point, name this activity opposed by William Lloyd Garrison and other abolitionists.", "answer": "<b><u>slavery</u></b> [or <b><u>holding slaves</u></b>, etc.]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Early in this conflict, Pelagius of Asturias won the Battle of Covadonga. During this conflict, the Almohads were defeated at the Battle of Las Navas de Tolosa. El Cid fought on both sides of this conflict, which was completed with the defeat of Granada by Ferdinand and Isabella. For the point, give this term for the long-running conflict in which Muslim kingdoms were expelled from the Iberian Peninsula.", "answer": "<b><u>Reconquista</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Mark Vieha wrote a long-running jingle for this product, which was invented by Jim Delligati in suburban Pittsburgh and originally called the Aristocrat. This item was promoted in the 1980s by a lounge singer whose face was a crescent moon. An index based on the price of this fast food item is used as a simple measure of local purchasing power by <em>The Economist</em>. For the point, name this double-decker burger, a signature product of McDonald\u2019s.", "answer": "<b><u>Big Mac</u></b> (prompt on hamburger, burger, etc.)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Rulers with this title allowed subjects to worship gods other than their own sky god Tengri. Meetings called <em>kurultai</em> elected these rulers, who issued a law code known as the <em>Yassa</em>. The first prominent holder of this title married B\u00f6rte (<b>BOR-tay</b>) before he subjugated the Khwarezmians. <em>Kamikaze</em> winds wrecked the navy of a holder of this title who also started the Yuan dynasty of China. For the point, name this warlord rank attained by Kublai and Genghis, two Mongols.", "answer": "<b><u>khan</u></b> (accept <b><u>Genghis Khan</u></b> or <b><u>Kublai Khan</u></b> if someone gives a full name instead)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The first of two themes representing Till Eulenspiegel (<b>TIL OY-len-shpee-gul</b>) is played by this instrument. Prominent Viennese musician Joseph Leutgeb (<b>LOYT-geb</b>) played this instrument, and debuted four concertos for it by Mozart. This instrument developed from a simpler device used in hunting and can be played with a technique invented in 1750 by Anton Joseph Hampel. For the point, name this brass instrument that is \"hand-stopped\" and sometimes named for a European country.", "answer": "French <b><u>horn</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Firestick farming was practiced by this supergroup of people, who lost land under the <em>terra</em> <em>nullius</em> doctrine. The Warlpiri people of Yuendumu are among these people, who were legally grouped with the Torres Strait islanders. A state policy to raise and educate mixed-race members of this group resulted in the Stolen Generations. For the point, name these indigenous people displaced by convicts transported to Botany Bay, many of whom revere Ayers' Rock as Uluru.", "answer": "Australian <b><u>aboriginal</u></b>s [or <b><u>aborigine</u></b>s; or <b><u>indigenous</u></b> people of <b><u>Australia]</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A drug lord with this alias was originally dubbed L-50 and was a leader of Los Zetas captured in 2012. While in power, this group banned the practice of Bacha bazi, or \u201cboy play\u201d. This group was responsible for destroying the Buddhas of Bamiyan and were originally funded by Pakistan\u2019s I-S-I. For the point, name this Islamic militant group headed by Mullah Mohammed Omar, which ruled Afghanistan until the 2001 US-led invasion.", "answer": "<b><u>Taliban</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This city took its modern form in 1784 when the Mala Strana, the Hradcany district, and its Old Town were united into one administrative entity. In 1620, the Count of Tilly routed Frederick V at White Mountain near this city. In 1618, two Catholic regents claimed they were saved by the intercession of Mary after being thrown from a window in this city. For the point, name this historical capital of Bohemia where a defenestration helped spark the 30 Years War.", "answer": "<b><u>Prague</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This city elected David Hanson Waite as mayor in 1893, leading to the \"City Hall War,\" which was ended by federal troops from Fort Logan. This city closed its Stapleton International Airport in 1995, following the construction of a 4.8 billion dollar replacement that is often the subject of conspiracy theories because its runways form a swastika. For the point, name this city, the capital of the Centennial State, which has been the largest in Colorado for decades.", "answer": "<b><u>Denver</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man's romantic life is the subject of Todd Compton's book <em>In Sacred Loneliness</em>. This man claimed to be able to read the \"Reformed Egyptian\" language using the seer stones Urim and Thummim. A mob riled up by the <em>Nauvoo Expositor</em> killed this man in Carthage, Illinois, after which he was succeeded by Brigham Young. For the point, name this man who was shown golden plates by the angel Moroni which he transcribed into the Book of Mormon.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>Smith</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This city's largest suburb was named for a pioneering Catholic bishop who owned the \"Jesus Island\" on which the city was founded. This city sits just to the south of that island on a larger member of the Hochelaga (<b>AWSH-leh-guh</b>) Archipelago, separated by the River of the Prairies. This city is home to the world's largest subterranean shopping complex, and still hosts soccer games at Olympic Stadium. For the point, name this most populous city in Quebec.", "answer": "<b><u>Montreal</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A November 2014 column by Eric Jackson accused this man of \"wasting a hundred billion dollars\" by performing stock buybacks and issuing dividends. An anti-discrimination bill introduced in the Alabama legislature in December 2014 was named for this man, a former Compaq VP who joined his current company in 1998. For the point, name this man who wrote a <em>Business Week</em> editorial in October entitled \"I'm Proud to Be Gay,\" and is the CEO of Apple.", "answer": "Tim <b><u>Cook</u></b> [Timothy Donald <b><u>Cook</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Off the coast of this colony, a group led by Abraham Whipple burned a British customs cutter during the <em>Gaspee</em> affair. This colony was where Anne Hutchinson went after being exiled from Massachussetts, because it was led by a dissenting proponent of church-state separation. For the point, name this colony which was founded by Roger Williams and included the cities of Newport and Providence.", "answer": "<b><u>Rhode Island</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "New examples of these structures have been found as recently as 1989, when J.C. Bhattacharyya found two of them. These structures were first correctly identified by Chrstian Huygens, who failed to notice the spaces in between them which are now named for their discoverer, Giovanni Cassini. For the point, name these structures which astronomers using the new telescopes found around the second-largest planet.", "answer": "<b><u>rings of Saturn</u></b> [prompt on partial answer]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s independence movement grew out of riots at the opera <em>The Mute Girl of</em> <em>Portici</em>. Carlota, Empress of Mexico, was the daughter of this country\u2019s first king. This country\u2019s king employed the explorer Henry Stanley and was condemned by the Casement Report. That king, who held the Congo Free State as his own possession, was Leopold II. For the point, name this low country in Western Europe whose neutrality Germany disregarded in World War I.", "answer": "<b><u>Belgium</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Democratic primaries for this year's election featured the second of two campaigns by Jesse Jackson, and the Democratic National Convention in this year featured a very long speech from then-little-known Bill Clinton. This election's winner ran the \"Willie Horton\" ad and promised \"read my lips, no new taxes.\" For the point, give this year in which Massachussetts governor Michael Dukakis lost the Presidential election to George H.W. Bush.", "answer": "19<b><u>88</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1979, this organization hired Green Bar Bill Hillcourt to eliminate changes it made during the prior decade which had decimated its membership. This organization was founded by W.D. Boyce, who was inspired by Robert Baden-Powell. This organization's firing of James Dale was upheld in a 2000 Supreme Court case, which addressed its policy barring gay leaders. For the point, name this organization, which teaches young Americans outdoor skills.", "answer": "<b><u>Boy Scouts</u></b> of America [or <b><u>BSA</u></b>]  <b>Extra (ONLY READ IF YOU BOTCH A QUESTION!) </b> In ancient China, Zhou dynasty objects of this usage that were shaped like spades with three holes in them were supplanted by objects resembling knives. The <em>ban liang</em> was replaced by the <em>wu zhu</em> for this purpose during the Han dynasty. The most notable Chinese objects for this purpose were decorated with four characters surrounding a square hole. For the point, name this type of tradeable object usually made of copper or bronze, exemplified by cast-made coins.  ANSWER: <b><u>money</u></b> [or <b><u>currency</u></b>; or <b><u>payment</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}